<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Beatson Microbial Genomics Lab</title><link>/</link><description>Microbial Genomics Laboratory</description><atom:link href="/feeds/nouri-ben-zakour.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 10:30:00 +1000</lastBuildDate><item><title>R scripts dedicated to statistical analysis of distribution of distances using various graphical representations and non-parametric tests</title><link>/didt-dist.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We point you to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/nbenzakour/DistanceDistributionAnalysis"&gt;DistanceDistributionAnalysis&lt;/a&gt; repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripts available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
distri-difference-generic.R: available now - still requires a bit of editing
distri-difference-ks-test_example-1.R: adapted to a particular case
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figures available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
distri-difference-ks-test_example-1_Figure.tif
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="strategy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the set of observed distances between 2 categories of
genomic regions (i.e., CAT1 and CAT2), we want to evaluate if they are
genetically linked or associated (biased towards being found closer than
expected by chance). In other words, if the positions of CAT1 are random with
respect to CAT2, the distribution of distances [CAT1-CAT2] should follow
a uniform distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="steps"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considers the observed distribution of N distances between CAT1 and CAT2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generates a random list of N distances in the same space of potential
distances. The expected distribution should be uniform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;creates a number of representations to visualise the 2 distributions
profiles, including: frequency histograms density plots cumulative
frequency plots boxplots qqplots...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tests whether the distributions are significantly different or not.
Non-parametric methods are used here, considering that a normal
distribution cannot be assumed for the data, especially as the second
object is already known to be uniform. Also determine the direction of
the shift if there is one and if possible e.g determine the negative
skew of the observed distances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Nouri Ben Zakour</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 10:30:00 +1000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-02-12:didt-dist.html</guid></item></channel></rss>